this is dr. Charles Parker and you're
listening to core brain journal it's a
place where I connect both fresh
discoveries and interesting different
perspectives from advanced mind science
with the realities of real people and
everyday life down on Main Street well
welcome folks here we are one more time
dr. Charles Parker this is core brain
journal and I'm gonna have to tell you
folks you just have to get ready I mean
if you're driving a car and you have
your seatbelt fastened that's a good
thing because if you're just around the
house or you're at the gym I suggest you
prepare to sit down and gather your
thoughts because we have a guest that is
going to burn your ears off and light up
your brain in all kinds of constructive
ways so welcome Daniel this is Daniel
smacking burger from Encinas California
welcome Daniel thanks for having me
really appreciate you coming on board
I'm going to introduce him and then
we're gonna hear a lot more about who he
is and how he's thinking about the
evolution of mind science so Daniel
smacking burger is the consummate
polymath with a background in system
science and human behavior and is the
founder of the emergence project he's
the anchor of the scientific team as
well as provides the vision behind neuro
hacking movement at neuro hacker.com
now some of you out there are saying
okay guys what is this whole neuro
hacker thing I'm gonna pass that one
over you Daniel and tell us a little bit
about yourself and how you got into the
whole neuro hacking movement please so
neuro hacking pretty much means applied
neuroscience how can we work with
various technologies and modalities to
increase various aspects of mind brain
function cognitive and psychological and
widely it is technology agnostic meaning
whether we're talking about biochemical
technologies or whether we're talking
about
neuro tech kinds of technologies like
transcranial stimulation transcranial
ultrasound transcranial magnetic deep
stem GDC ST ACS any of those kinds of
technologies or whether we're talking
about brain training via neurofeedback
or any other kind of brain training or
whether we're talking about genomic
solutions in terms of either modulating
gene expression or CRISPR technologies
or psychotherapeutic or any kind of
personal development technologies
anything that is affecting the mind
brain system and the associated
physiology environment systems that can
optimize human experience and human
capability we're interested in well
Daniel I'm glad that you summarized it
so succinctly but you just covered the
entire field of mind science in about
two sentences I think it's amazing that
you were able to do that but I like the
idea of technology agnostic
because you're saying let's be inclusive
let's not get all of our ducks in one
row let's think about these in a from a
complexity point of view and you and I
had an opportunity to speak about this
earlier and I think that whole thing of
complexity systems if you could talk a
little bit about that and how pulling
these disparate ideas together might be
constructive
yeah when the field of psycho norm
ecology started complex system science
was not well developed wasn't really
developed at all and so our best
scientific methodology was still
variable isolation reductionism so we're
looking specifically to try and
understand what dopamine does or what a
particular molecule that affects some
part of you the dopamine system a
presynaptic dopamine agonist or a
dopamine receptor modulator you know
some some particular part of it what
that does but that means we're trying to
understand one part in isolation of the
rest of the whole and to be able to do
clinical trials on that appropriately
we're kind of averaging everything else
together and then we see do we get some
kind of statistical lift beyond placebo
and if we do then that seems interesting
even though that
bell curve has people getting
significantly different experiences on
opposite ends the bell curve
they're obviously attributable to other
things right the way that one variables
interfacing with the rest of the system
and so complex system science allows us
to look at a lot more variables a lot
more complexly and look at their
interactions and their synergies synergy
defined as the behavior of whole systems
that is unpredicted by the behavior of
the parts taken separately in isolation
and so one of the problems when we were
trying to isolate variables is the
synergies between variables get missed
and this is why and the way we've
practiced medicine we have
gastroenterology neurology oncology etc
all the diseases that start in one
system and move to another system right
issues that start in the gut caused
mucosal barrier dysfunction and end up
causing neurologic issues because
they're between systems we end up
missing so much of the pathology of the
passo etiology and what we find is also
in radically complex systems everything
to various degrees intersects everything
else so we need to study that that the
causal interactions much more complexly
we also get causal recursion where one
thing can affect another variable but
then that variable can in turn come back
and riaf echt that variable both either
in a regulatory capacity or with
positive feedback loops and so obviously
when we look at the success of
psychiatric medicine for all kinds of
psych diseases currently compared to
what a system that was really adequate
for addressing them would be we have a
huge Delta and the fields of integrative
psychiatry North Molecular Psychiatry
you know interdisciplinary approaches to
mind brain science have started to look
at a lot more variables right rather
than just give a in chain neuro chemical
modulator in the form of a med look at
why did that chemical get off balance in
the first place and really was it just
that one chemical is it a whole set of
things they got out of balance and did
it originate in an inflammatory
condition in a gut condition in a
psychological condition and head trauma
right
and then we also start to see that not
only are there a lot of variables that
are involved but they're different sets
of variables for different people and
this is where we start to get towards
personalized medicine and then
personalized psychology psychiatry and
personalized development so say we're
looking at anxiety or autism or
Alzheimer's and we're looking at all the
things that we know causally are
associated right or at least all the
things where we have a some kind of
correlation and so we'll find maybe
heavy metals are actually statistically
meaningfully correlated with this
particular kind of neurodegenerative
disease but so are other forms of Organa
toxin of organic toxins right
organophosphates VOCs maybe microbial
imbalances in the mucosal system may be
parasitic infections may be subclinical
humeral infections may be methylation
disorders may be certain kinds of
psychological disorders you see all of
these things are correlated but not one
for one which means they statistically
correlate there probably have a causal
influence sometimes but not all the time
because that represents one pathway of
deviation from homeostasis that can lead
to pathophysiology that can lead to some
set of symptomology occurring and when
we talk about anxiety or Alzheimer's or
any kind of disease what we're talking
about is some similar kinds of symptoms
from some similar kinds of tissues but
the underlying pathologist can be quite
different that's why we haven't
succeeded in really being able to
address them and so you need to develop
an underlying causal landscape a causal
ontology of all the things that could be
associated it could be causal how to do
differential diagnosis across all of
those and then how to be able to
understand different therapies in terms
of the underlying mechanisms that are
involved and then what is the weighted
subset of that whole causal landscape
that's going on for this person and then
what what therapies what synergy of
therapies and in what order of
operations are going to be ideal to them
and this is where we move towards real
personalized medicine personalized
psychotherapy and then be
on the baseline of wellness personalized
enhancement and development that gets to
synthesize the best of everything that
we know today
you know while you're talking you say
it's so exceedingly well I'm pardon me
for being effusive with you a little bit
but it's just so interesting to hear you
talk because it's what so many of us
struggle with every day it doesn't
matter whether you're a purely
traditional psyche or whether you're a
patient coming into a psychosis
everybody's looking for the complexity
really in their mind they're thinking
complexity but they don't have a vehicle
a road a path to consider and wrap their
arms around complexity and there may
additional thing where the complexity is
not only the variables that you're
speaking about but is the complexity of
time as time comes in to the whole
situation because so much of function is
time related and so much of what we're
dealing with is not time related it's
fine that label to be that way to the
next hundred years yeah we also have
when there were at the time we have all
of the conditions that have very delayed
causation delayed onset and this is
something that always makes diagnosis
tricky is if something has a rapid onset
following a pretty clear cause it's a
little bit easier to treat but if
something has either a rapid onset but
not following any clear cause or maybe
the clear cause that it followed was
simply a last trigger of a whole causal
chain that moved it in the symptomology
then it's very easy to miss attribute it
and so we need to be able to do
diagnosis thinking about things that
might have happened a long time ago but
not resulted in some Tamala G and then
as we as we're treating of course here's
one of the things I would say is very
deep to our goals is we have this
internal regulatory system right this
endogenous regulatory system and it's
not one regulatory system but you can
think of all the different regulatory
axes as a comprehensive regulatory or
cybernetic system and we're regulating
pH and redox interactions and glucose
and you know transmitters you know all
the
within specific ranges so if someone's
dopamine is really low and I just give
them a in chain dopamine that agonist
without asking why was it low was it low
because they aren't eating enough
protein that contains the amino acid
precursors is it because they can't
digest the protein because of a issue in
their stomach they can't absorb it
because of an issue and their intestines
can they not convert those amino acids
can they not convert the tyrosine into
l-dopa into dopamine are there enzyme
deficiencies are there so if I go
straight to giving the in chain agonist
and of course whatever else was affected
downstream I'm not going to be
supporting right and say it was say it
was a tyrosine mechanism well that's
also affecting their thyroid or it is
also affecting so many other systems and
I'm going to get some side effects
because now I'm creating a fixed level
of that chemical independent of the
body's real-time regulation of it which
is gonna throw out the balance with the
you know literally trillions of other
chemicals that it should be interacting
with with more complexity than that and
I'm creating exogenous dependence right
so rather than the body being able to
self-regulate it's depending on external
regulation and so now there's ongoing
dependence our goal is that any good
system of medicine and good system of
psychiatry and good system of biohacking
neuro hacking should be supporting the
endogenous regulatory systems to have
increased regulatory capacity and we can
really define health as the robustness
and resilience of the regulatory
capacity of the entire system and then
we can think about aging actually as
decreased homeostatic resilience on some
of the axes and then we can think about
disease as some deviations from
homeostasis that exceed the homeostatic
capacity of one or more of the axes that
lead to pathophysiology so then our goal
really becomes in preventing illness in
life extension and in fundamental
optimization of the human experience and
condition
how do we increase the resilience the
robustness and the antifragility
of the entire set of regulatory systems
and a good intervention should seek to
do that right it should seek to support
endogenous upregulation rather than
overwrite it well you know one of the
things that as you're talking I'm sure
the complexity of your thinking is so
fascinating but I said something there
just at the very close that I wanted to
jump on because what you're really
saying in a way and correct me if I'm
wrong is that we're really dealing when
you're dealing with the complexity you
have a complexity of answers you don't
have a single answer so one of the
things that happens is people come a guy
like me and they say you know I've got
this problem well how come I have to do
all these supplements and these
medicines and all these other things
because there are so many things can't
you just give me one thing and you know
I'm a very primitive level of this
understanding compared to where you are
but I think that's an interesting issue
to address with our our audience because
that's a frequent problem for our
audience how do we actually deal with
the complexity on a street level right I
would say the Silver Bullet mentality is
a broken mentality in every area every
area that we apply it whether we're
hoping that the answer to getting our
finances together is a lottery ticket or
the answer to getting buff or
psychologically well or anything it's it
always requires any kind of development
of any system requires continuous varied
kinds of input and entropy is always
acting on systems and so there is a
minimum and it's acting on on all
systems right you have oxidative stress
on cells you have excitotoxin stress you
have mutation that's occurring you've
got and so it's you've got entropy
occurring on all these systems you need
to be putting in at least as much energy
and by energy here I don't mean glucose
and Jaime putting in at least as much of
the appropriate kind of input as is
eroding and to just even keep up right
and just like anyone knows that if
someone works out for ten years
gets buff as can be the moment they stop
working out they start losing it and it
is entropies it's just kind of universal
recycling process of that which is not
no longer useful right and so then it
starts moving those parts to be used for
something else so any kind of health any
kind of resilience requires continuous
input and the appropriate kinds of
continuous input so we know that there
are so many different minerals depending
upon which list you read of how many are
essential at 72 or 84 or 92 right but
there's so many minerals that are
essential for health there's so many
vitamins so many phytonutrients so many
macronutrients and even a deficiency of
one of them can lead to a debilitating
disease right just D being low leading
the rickets or C being well leading the
scurvy or b1 leading a beriberi and so
Liam if we want to not see it's not just
them being low enough that they go into
acute pathology it's also the sub
clinical pathology of systems that are
working they're just not working
optimally and now we're not just talking
about nutrients in but we're also
talking about input that supports detox
and input that supports antioxidant
anti-inflammatory
but it is part of what's going to
support system regulation so yes I would
say that anyone who wants to be really
healthy and vital and optimized has to
take full responsibility for what that
means and not expect that there's a very
easy doctor solution or a single kind of
solution and just embrace that as the
the physics of universe I mean that is
so absolutely true I mean that is what
we deal with either we're going to deal
with
complexity now and and some of us may be
interested in how do we package the
complexity because ya do have to
understand the complexity they can't
just go out and shotgun the complexity
because that absolutely won't work it
has to honor the integrity of the system
in some constructive way and even though
there there is a complexity involved
that the integrity of that system has to
have somehow be packaged in a way that
the person on the street can actually
you know what's what's a what's a good
systems approach to that particular
problem right when I think what you're
doing with the podcast here is offering
people education so that they can feel
more empowered in what are likely
appropriate avenues for them to dive
deeper into what we're seeking to do
over at no hacker collective is no we're
we're developing specific technologies
they can go direct to consumer right now
we're developing more that might not go
direct to consumer but be you know
mediated by some kind of therapists but
what we're really looking to do long
range is a platform that allows us to
integrate all the kinds of complexity
personalize them to an individual and
their goals and actually make the
interface very simple for them and so if
we can collect all of people's
biometrics it from their genetics to
their clinical chemistry to their
quantified self sleep tracker motion
tracker whatever we can take all those
biometric data pieces and we can take
psycho metrics we can do cognitive
assessments that look at various aspects
of cognitive function and psychographic
assessments psychoanalytic assessments
then and then not just look at each of
those metrics in relationship to their
own reference range but look at each of
them in relationship to each other how
did this particular picture arise in
terms of factoring all of the underlying
inter causal dynamics then we can start
to get a real picture of
what's going on for someone and you know
this person's sleep disordered different
than this person sleep disorder right
this person's anxiety different than
this person's in terms of underlying
mechanics in terms of the you know
genetics and fundamental space of that
person and then be able to synthesize
what are all of the technologies that do
have known efficacy for sleep and then
relate them to underlying mechanics or
anxiety or whatever it is and then be
able to say these ones are going to be
most effective for this person at this
time you know highest probability so
this is N equals one optimization the
clinical trial can't do that right it
can only say there is some lift with a
bell curve compared to placebo even
though the people on one in the bell
curve and the other having totally
different experiences when you try to
put everybody on the front of the bell
curve now we're not saying okay I have
this device or supplements or meditation
technology or whatever I'm going to give
it to ruin because I have a hammer I'm
gonna saying that everything is a nail
right and we can say you have anxiety so
take a Benz or you have anxiety so do
this breathing technique or meditation
technique and it might help some but if
the person's anxiety is related to a
parasitic brain access disorder none
either those solutions are gonna fix it
and if it's related to a head trauma and
there's some actual neural circuitry to
address none of those are gonna fix it
but that doesn't mean there aren't
things that could fix it and it doesn't
mean that they wouldn't show up
differently if we know how to do the
right assessments and then be able to
direct people to you know what is the
highest probability of greatest success
for them which is actually now not that
complicated but it draws on all the
complexity of everything we know both
about psychology physiology the mind
brain interface and all of the
diagnostic and therapeutic modalities so
it has a simultaneous activity of ruling
out and ruling in so it's not just yep
ruling out Frank its ruling in and and
that's a very very interesting point
because that takes us over to the
affirmative prospect of how does this
thing actually work effective
as opposed to here's what the problem is
here's how we can see this pathology
okay this is this is a sick broken
system you're saying well that's really
only above the picture and if we get
lost over there which I think in truth
many of us are then we're arrested we're
developmentally arrested we have a lot
of great insights right in the world of
integrative medicine and functional
medicine I think have been doing a good
job
aggressively of trying to see how do we
factor more systems so we're gonna look
at the gastroenterology and the
neurology and the oncology and
Rheumatology together right and then
we're gonna look at the various
intercostal worlds together the genomics
and the microbiome X and the
transcriptomics and the proteomics and
the you know that way of looking at the
body and we're gonna look at the
different kinds of deviations from
homeostasis toxins nutrient deficiencies
genetic disorders infections right and
how do we work with those and try and
make some sense out of this and so you
can see various people who are kind of
at the cutting edge in those spaces
doing a better job of synthesizing more
things now synthesizing and aggregating
are different right aggregating is the
shotgun approach which just says all
right well all these have some
effectiveness let's kind of try all of
them synthesis is well these ones are
effective for for these kinds of
mechanisms not just these kinds of
insane conditions they can have lots of
mechanisms leading into them so how do
we do the differential diagnosis and
know what to do then for that person and
how do we do right order of operations
right so if it's functional medicine
gets into quite a lot when you need to
treat a gut barrier disorder before
trying to address blood toxicity issues
otherwise you're gonna can or
Rheumatology because you're going to
keep having inflammation from from tight
Junction issues whatever so I think
they're doing a very good job but
they're doing it like you go to a
conference and you look at all the
cutting-edge research that's happening
in various fields it's more than any
human can actually synthesize and when
you look at all the medical journals
that are coming out
actually good underlying mechanistic
insights it's again more than any human
can synthesize which is why it takes
this kind of AI platform methodology to
be able to vet and synthesize at scale
and then make all of human knowledge
available to individual practitioners
and individual people so I was like a
Wikipedia of the mind some constructive
way yes yes AI is artificial
intelligence yes just to say that
because I know some of our listeners may
wonder what AI is though
so then the next question after that is
do you you are developing a system then
you're developing ways of doing this and
you're codifying and how you know is
this going to happen in a computer model
of some kind is it going to be it sounds
like you're going in that direction that
when you feed the material in and you do
a certain and number of tests then you
can feed it in and pop something out
that's going to be more easily
accessible than then just plain thinking
it through yeah definitely so you can
see that we already have labs that
automate some of the suggestions based
on kind of standard protocols from what
they see in the lab so you get the lab
back and you have depending upon say
your doing them you know gut barrier
assessment then based on what's showing
up in the lab you'll see some generated
pages of common best practices you also
already have systems of electronic
medical records that start putting some
pieces of the data together start giving
you some analytics so that's the trend
in that direction those are just
relatively low intelligence systems and
so what what is interesting is as we can
start harvesting a lot more biometric
data then it becomes less and less
understandable by an
vidual person in real time so if we
start doing whole genome sequences and
want to look at the whole genome right
that's a lot it's and then it's not just
looking at individuals snips right
individual genes and their polymorphisms
it's looking at the combinatorics on
that and now that scales very quickly
and then that still doesn't tell you
about gene expression and so then we're
looking at clinical chemistry and
metabolomics transcriptomics etc and so
but all we can understand the underlying
mechanisms that are happening and we can
build systems to be able to model this
better and do a better job of making
more sense of more different kinds of
data in a synthesized fashion so that's
the goal I mean how can you say hold
that in one breath
I mean it's so interesting you know so
then how are you actually breaking that
down in neuro hacker I mean I don't want
to ask for any proprietary but just a
little bit of an idea because it sounds
so very large to the questions you're
raising or so enormous in terms of
practical how does one do that to make
it yeah well if you go to you know
hacker comm right now you won't see
anything about anything we're talking
about you will see a little bit of
information on complexity science
applied to neuroscience and you will see
some cognitive enhancement supplements
for sale so we're a relatively new
organization and so we're starting
somewhere like every organization needs
to and for us well we knew the goal was
C I'm talking about diagnostic methods
here but let's look at the therapeutic
side for a moment and you've got the
disease model side which is you know how
do we get people back to wellness from
some diagnosed disease but then you have
the enhancement side and so neuro hacker
has started in terms of its forward
facing offerings on the
direct-to-consumer enhancement side
and if you think of neural hacking kind
of as a subset of biohacking that is
specifically focused and and that just
means applied technologies for personal
enhancement but we're specifically
focused on the mind brain space so
enhancing cognitive and enhancing
emotional and psychological both
well-being and capability there's a lot
of different technologies that are
effective as we were mentioning you know
so we were looking at whether we wanted
to develop better systems of EEG
neurofeedback
or better systems of transcranial lasers
for up regulating neuronal ATP or better
systems of computer-based psychotherapy
or that can you know work on a widely
through a platform or the better kind
better kinds of neural chemical
solutions and they're all very
meaningful and they're differently
meaningful for different kinds of people
and so our goal is to synthesize to be
able to have a space where if someone
had a goal no matter what the goal was
in the psychoneurosis and no matter what
the underlying physiology they had going
on there could be a best synthesized
resource for them and so we started in
the know tropic space of cognitive
enhancement because we work in that
space deeply and we knew that we could
do very potent of life enhancing things
for people that were not currently
available on the market and we could do
that easier than we could build this AI
system and so this was a and then you
know from there a whole line of
direct-to-consumer biochemistry so
specific kinds of nutraceuticals that we
didn't see on the market anywhere else
because we're working with this complex
systems framework of not trying to say
alright we're we have a sleep mode and
we're working with gaba or melatonin or
you know but what are all the things
that are involved and how do we up
regulate the endogenous circuitry and
obviously to do this at full scale we
need to be able to do it in a customized
fashion
and that's what requires this underlying
system so we're starting with not
customized but center of the bell curve
very effective for most people and
that's what we currently have then we're
moving into phenotype specific so before
it's fully personalized we find that
there are handfuls of kind of
neurochemical phenotypes so like in the
Walsh work you've looked at under and
over meth later is a different
underlying structure right under an over
catecholamine urja under an over
cholinergic CNS stimulation so we can
get more affective just through those
kind of categories and then move into
full customization but it's also of all
the things one could do how likely is a
vagal nerve stimulator versus a
transcranial stimulator versus this
breathing technique versus these
biochemical gaba Eric's going to be most
useful for them even at that level so we
started building technologies in each of
these categories some are in market
already some are still in R&D and over
the next year a lot will be going coming
to market and this allows us to be able
to grow our research team and you know
continue development and the underlying
platform we're working on but you know
that that has some years before its
meaning meaningfully applicable well the
issue is because you're just going to
have you're really in kind of a data
acquisition mode from what you're saying
you're you you know generally what the
problem is but then you're codifying and
breaking it down and doing some serious
data acquisition because then you can
push the button and have some configure
so yeah we are as far as that
acquisition goes not mostly in terms of
feedback from current things we're doing
that's useful this is why we do trials
but it is doing
doing structured reviews of all of the
fields to know where the current state
of the art is of the entire field if you
synthesize all the knowledge which is
something that is not for whatever
reason commonly done or well done and
then being able to see what should our
hypothesis generation within a
particular space be once we already have
looked at everything that is known in
that space and what we can abstract from
all those partial insights together and
as you know if you're doing that in
connectomics if you're doing that in you
know neurogenesis if you're doing that
in genomics it's there's a lot of you
know takes work yeah yeah that's it's
deep it's gonna it's gonna cost I mean
to do that to actually pull the
laboratory data together it's gonna be
you have some interested people and some
well trained people and people who are
thinking along the same path who have
the same delightfully curiosity
objectives that you have it could happen
I mean it's just the question of putting
putting kind of a forgive the grandiose
expression kind of a new world order of
how do we how do we codify Dada how do
we pull it together yeah and the poet
together is the key part because machine
learning assessing big data is already
there and there's a number of systems
doing that but when the interactions are
as complex as these ones are even
tremendous amounts of computation don't
give us all the insights just via
computational brute force you have to
actually develop models you have to
develop underlying ontology of how this
complex human regulatory system works
and then be able to utilize those models
as ways of interpreting the data and
that's one of the things that we're kind
of uniquely focused on sounds so
interesting so when you go over to the
website we have some
I've seen them you have some great
videos that break down some of this I
mean it's been a while since I was over
there you're looking like maybe you
trying to think of which video was that
it seemed to me there was a video that I
saw is like oh my gosh this I had a very
interesting interesting moment and I am
I miss remembering that I think we have
some videos on the site currently I
don't know that we have any speaking
about the future of say Diagnostics or
interpretation like this but we do have
ones that are discussing why a system
heights approach is needed and then some
of how we came up with this particular
cognitive enhancement chemistry from a
systems theoretic perspective and
because it's not only useful for
interpreting diagnostic that it's also
useful building technologies that work
across multiple mechanisms
simultaneously and one understand the
synergy of those mechanisms so when
we're talking about enhancing people's
cognitive capability are we talking
about modifying acetylcholine or
glutamate or dopamine or other
catecholamines or ion channels or
changing the phospholipid membranes or
we're probably talking about all of
those things right and so and then with
acetylcholine that are we talking about
changing how it gets across the synapse
are we talking about changing how it is
up taken and the postsynaptic receptor
or we and so what we did in that space
because there are so many people who are
not using adderall via prescription but
off-label adderall and other kind of
what you call smart drugs for their
midterms their finals their tech startup
where it really does have meaningful
side-effects and and even you know Red
Bull and multiple doses of 300
milligrams of caffeine with it's
important to get that both something
like adderall and both something like
the energy drinks will enhance a certain
element
of productivity and focus while
decreasing statistically known to
decrease other key elements of cognitive
capability plus producing dependents
plus producing side-effects and so we
wanted to see can we support people in
their desire to be more clear and
productive and capable in the presence
of ever increasing attention
distractions in ways that are more
effective and not harmful and so that
that required us looking at well when
people are really seeking cognitive
enhancement what are they looking for
and they're not just looking for focus
they're looking for a combination of
focus and short-term memory and
long-term memory and speed of memory and
specific memory and digit span and
verbal fluency and emotional things that
come along with it like emotional Raziel
and Adams connection to drive and so we
kind of from a cognitive science point
of view modeled what is everything that
people look for there and then we looked
at what is everything known about the
underlying physiologic pathway is known
to correlate with each of those
subjective States and cognitive
capabilities then there's chemistry that
affects all of those pathways and then
start our design process from there so
that's you know a systems theoretic
perspective works both on may slide
design science and they interpreting
Diagnostics in both of those worlds so
the question then is a guy who practices
sort of proprietary question but I'm
curious because I use testing and I
wonder how a person like you or your
team decides which group you're going to
use for the tests that you're going to
acquire so that it could have a more
diffused body position so that so that a
number of people can use it effectively
how do you actually decide what the
laboratory is going to be or which
laboratories to use how does that happen
yeah so as far as laboratory testing
goes I have to make my FDA disclaimer
statement right now we're talking about
the future of medicine and psychiatry
just abstractly but as far as neuro
hacker goes we don't have anything to
say about medicine or psychiatry because
we can't say anything about that and we
aren't prescribing labs and etc so we
just tell people to go to a doctor and
get those done but as far as research in
that space coast how do we determine how
would I determine what I think is a good
laboratory test or not well there's a
few things first we have to look at
sensitivity and specificity
how many false negatives how many false
positives do we have from that lab by
comparing it to other known best of
assessments over an appropriate database
so that's kind of pretty standard and
then we have to look at the turnaround
time for getting the data back we have
to look at the cost of it and all other
aspects of viability and then we have to
look at how relevant the data that it's
showing us is and and what the
interpretive confidence margin around
clinical applications from that data
looks like and so you know if we're
doing parasitology and we really were
just interested in do we see the
parasite right but if we're doing some
immunology connected to parasitology and
we're running CD 57 to say that someone
has Lyme's disease but we know that it's
not actually specific to Lyme it could
be all kinds of infections then a CD 57
for me means some kind of humoral
infection usually and that's about all
it means right so I can use it as a
indicator along with many other
indicators for a complex set of
assessments but I have to be careful
about my how I interpret that particular
metric now as far as the platform that
we're interested in we want to make a
platform that can upload any tests right
so whether someone's comprehensive stool
lab is coming from doctors data or
Genova or whatever
right if the sensitivity and specificity
is known to be high enough to the
meaningful confidence margin we won't be
able to upload any of them and be able
to run data interpretation across them
in the future but it's also important to
know that I'm very passionate about
developing diagnostic technologies
further because when when we want to do
complex complex disease case solutions
in particular I I want to look at all of
the inflammatory markers all the
autoimmune all the rheumatologic markers
right I want to look at all of the kind
of nutrient markers I look at all the
genetics that I can see oh and look at
all the clinical chemistry all because
it ends up being that even some of the
more obscure things show up and that you
wouldn't have thought to be associated
show up in many of the difficult cases
and non-obvious ways and so to even say
order of operations of which diagnosis
to do first which to later I'd rather
get them all cheaper all more reliable
and be able to just do a lot more data
on everybody and so there are kinds of
technology that could make that possible
like being able to do metabolomics on
mass spectrometry could make metabolomic
as has my very cheap and in near future
right across 2500 metabolites be able to
continuously run those and things like
you know single drop of blood on the
technology like gene radar is getting
very interesting and the next step
beyond that is I think laser
interferometry where we can test a
number of elements in the blood just
through scattering patterns diffraction
patterns on laser light going in you
could imagine if that technology got
very far that we could testing all of
the biometrics nearly continuously
running big data on those and you can
imagine how much we could learn and so
that those are things that we see in the
future of medicine that's an amazing
picture because what you're talking
about is measuring you know the things
that you're measuring are phenomenal
because you're actually talking about
all kinds of different pieces of the
body so to speak you know anything from
extra meant to urine to mouth swabs to
you know a lot of there's a lot of
biomedical variables in that whole
situation that you were talking about
many of which I don't know about myself
because I'm just a commonplace
practitioner I while I'm listening to
you I'm amazed because I'm thinking of
my own self discovery process while I'm
listening to you and how I was going
along thinking hey this really worked
but then it did so then I went into
another level and say oh this works but
hey here's another place for this new
thing that I learned but it doesn't work
so it's been one long process for me on
a on a personal level of finding these
different things that is why I value
speaking to a person like yourself who
has this this depth of knowledge with
these like that whole thing is they
spectral with the blood cell what was
that what was that called you had some
you're shooting laser into was laser and
laser interferometry is there's very
little that I can access right now and
we're not sure how much we'll be able to
assess but I I have a hope the dance
will be a lot and so the deal there is
you're actually just putting a beam of
light coherent light into say your wrist
vein and then it bounces back but based
on what's in the blood what molecules
are in the blood the frequencies of
light will scatter and they'll scatter
differently based on different molecules
and different densities of them so you
can tell blood glucose without taking
one drop of blood right but then the
question is which molecules in the blood
could we assess and could it be a lot
more of them and could it be mostly all
of them and so whether it's mass spec on
urine doing you know metabolites or
whether it's lilies or interferometry or
who knows
far out bio field assessments I think I
think we what we know for sure is we
will be able to get more and
more data more often more Rubik wit
ously so that we can understand patterns
across lots of people but even within a
single person and as that happens it
progressively exceeds the ability of
individual people to understand fully
without some aid in processing and
that's where as the diagnostic
technologies get better the
interpretative technologies need to get
better and that's about the
interpretative models that the doctors
and people can learn but also processing
those the data through those models so
to translate a little bit if you take
some of these labs like Genova Great
Plains or whatever you and you find some
level of confluence of successful
information from them that would just be
a piece of what you're envisioning
because they would only cover the
dimension that that lab is skilled at
great right and so you have to then have
a number of different you have to have a
not one module that you have to have
several different modules it's just
going to be worked up and you have to
figure out integrate and synthesize
those modules into into one at once I
shouldn't say one answer but one series
of answers right so I'm not a I'm not a
doctor I'm a researcher but I've worked
with a number of Integrative doctors on
difficult
traditionally incurable cases and we're
so we looked at what are all the things
that the literature knows is initially
correlated and then how do we assess for
those and that would look like I would
have a relationship with one lab to test
Michael plasmas and another one to test
viruses and another one to test
parasitology and protozoa and another
one for the best Rheumatology and other
ones for scans and that was actually
usually several different types for
different kinds of brain scans and other
ones from you coastal barrier function
right and other ones for mold and
biotoxin information the other ones for
environmental toxins and so what that
means is that's just so burdensome on
the
Nishan and on the office staff have to
set up all those relationships send them
different places and spend the blood
this way and etc that we really need the
field of Diagnostics to get
fundamentally better otherwise some
diseases are incurable that aren't
really incurable simply because what it
takes to figure them out is too hard
that is so true we see that every day
I mean the the whole spectrum of how you
actually just get the test taking it
requires you know forget managed care
and answering it to myriads of people in
managed care who with high school
education below that is how do you just
fill out the paperwork and get to get
the laboratory information back to to
pull it together and then how do you
spend the time to put it together and
get a and and put together a program for
a person yeah it's great it's definitely
difficult right now why are you why
you're talking I was thinking about an
experience I had with some really
interesting neurofeedback people when I
add the office up in DC he mo
encephalography when you were talking
about that particular technique because
even now and people out there need to
know that you could put a band on and
shoot red infrared spectrums
near-infrared hemo and encephalography
you can shoot it right through the skull
have it bounce out and get readings on
what's going on with the oxygenation and
the prefrontal cortex
yeah and that's there that's here right
now which is and it's not difficult to
do I mean the technology is pretty
doggone simple to do require I should
say it's true well yeah I mean the s
near technology is pretty simple easy
technology and EEG is becoming simple
enough that home EEG units are actually
meaning meaningful data sources and home
HRV units are good and so this is one
what's the HRV
heart rate variability okay and so we
which is a major indicator of autonomic
nervous system
um and so there it this whole field what
we call quantified self the various
kinds of devices that allows health
measurement I think is going to be a
huge part of the future of medicine
where people take more and more
responsibility for their own well-being
and this means that already people have
the ability to buy their own supplements
and you know do a number of their own
therapeutic modalities but they also
they need to be able to track right if
it if they really want to understand
what's going on and so I think both of
those are increasing yeah track your
time because they're gonna be able to do
that assessment and then that'll be
somehow hooked back to your database of
hey it's working or no it's not and
right it's not what do we do next
so this is in the Dreaming phase for us
in terms of all the things at that
platform we'll be able to do but we do
hope that it gets to the place where we
can do the kinds of complex data
processing we're talking about and
included then is if there is data
missing that we would need to be able to
figure it out that we can actually
recommend what kind of diagnostics
people get we could recommend doctors
for them to go work within a network but
we could also be able to recommend which
of the home assessment technologies are
best from vetting them so that you know
we're empowering people to have more
ability to participate in their own
well-being now that's a reason for all
of our listeners to go right over to
neuro hacker and get hooked up
immediately because they need to be on
your list right now because if you then
have next week or next month or next
year some way of beginning this process
of measurement that you folks have
signed off on that you think is going to
be valid and useful then they need to be
there I mean our whole audience this
ours is a small audience I mean there's
a bigger audience out there that's
curious about this but I think anybody
that ever listens to this should be just
immediately hooked up with neuro hacker
I'm quite enthusiastic about
having had the chance to speak with you
because what you're talking about is
where we're I think so many people want
to be but don't know how to get there
myself included I think you know you
know it's it's such an interesting place
to be and to even envision the
possibilities are there because the mind
does seem you know completely out there
it's just we can't even talk about it
it's just over our heads nothing to talk
about all these different things
IgG is still complex if as mundane is
that simple test is a lot of people it's
a belief system to some you know it's
still it's this Galileo moment you know
the Sun is rotating around Rome I know
it is I can see it is so we don't need
to worry about that and that that is
what's going on so we really do have to
close Daniel I really I know you're a
little bit under the weather and I can't
tell you how much I appreciate you
taking the time to join or join us here
and and be with our audience I mean this
is gonna be one of our most outstanding
interviews because why because people
are going to have to listen to it more
than once because you are so deep and so
interesting that people are going to are
going to share this and really be
interested to learn more from you so
thank you very much appreciate it dr.
Parker at so much respect for what
you're doing and it was a real honor to
be here thanks for listening to core
brain journal we're working every day
behind the scenes to bring you reports
that connect research benches with those
street trenches here we share the
complexity of mine science because as
you know details really do matter one of
the most pervasive misunderstood
challenges is how commonplace
medications like those written for ADHD
are used so regularly without clear
guidelines if you think you'd like more
specifics take a minute to download my
two page PDF packed with video links and
references on the absolute essentials of
how to start ADHD medications they're
easily available at core brain journal
com
forward-slash start thanks for listening
do connect and stay tuned together we
can make a difference
[Music]